so the question is how practices of
Labor's or rather how to make progress
in as a householder so in your household
life how to develop your Dharma practice
further the first point would be to
recognize that well we said it before
that you are responsible for your
environment so if you're a household
they have to take responsibility for
choosing to remain so and same like if
you choose to stop being a householder
and go for become a monk or a nun again
you will be responsible for your actions
and consequences that would come out of
it
the reason why people would try and
avoid a responsibility for that for
whatever they are for the things they
chose to do and now they have to live
with the results of those things it's
because it would make you feel guilty so
to speak so if you for example youíve
value in value practice of the Dhamma
you want to progress in the Dhamma but
you have to look after a family now that
family hasn't been sort of thrown upon
you it's a it's a result of your actions
of your choices before maybe before you
came across the Dhamma but nevertheless
you are responsible for it so even if
now you would like to not have to look
after other people because you want to
dedicate your life to practicing the
Dhamma you can't because you you've made
such actions you've done such actions
and choices that have resulted in other
people being dependent upon you so you
have to recognize that you are
responsible for the environment and that
means that you cannot use environment as
an excuse so there is a difference there
there's a difference between you
accepting responsibility and not
excusing yourself for not practicing
further because of the environment but
more often than not what people do is
they don't accept responsibility in a
sense of they might accept
responsibility on the surface but
underneath they they still
and have pretty much a view that the
environment excuses you from not
practicing further but that's that's not
the case so you choose then environment
to become a reason a justification for
your lack of further practice so even
even as a household that doesn't matter
so the point is to accept that
responsibility and that means not use
your environment as an excuse for your
lack of development for you know for
still being a petitioner for example not
being free from suffering so you want to
you want to you want to kind of remove
that attitude because it does it just
removes any basis for correct practice
for as long as you're covering it up so
you've actually recognized that other
people's lives might be compromised if
you stop looking after them beat your
children responses your parents but at
the same time you've actually do not use
that as an excuse for not practicing so
that will kind of force you to to make
or force you into a maximum effort
within that compromised environment and
this ties in with my next point which is
a sense restraint precepts and even
celibacy often people would argue that
they cannot become a monk or a nun
because they have to look after the
family which is factually correct but
then that fact would somehow jump into a
justification that they because of that
they don't also need to be sense
restraint and and those are two
completely separate things so yes you
don't have to ordain and become a monk
but that it's not to say that you can
also not a practice sense restrain and
develop in Dhamma so in simple terms
people find a certain
[Music] factual basis of needing to stay a
factual basis of needing to stay a
layman orderly woman but then the
factual basis because it's not taking
responsibility in the sense we just
described that factual basis then
becomes an excuse and as such it becomes
a blanket excuse blanket excuse for not
accepting sorry blank blanket excuse for
not going not going forth but then also
blankly excuse for now because I'm not
going forth I don't need to practice
sense restraint here either and as I
said those are two separate things you
can you can stay layman for the rest of
your life and that's one thing but if
you choose that me being a layman means
I don't have to be sensory strain and
practice the Dharma that's just the
contradiction in terms of no.4 on all
sorts of levels so and by the way this
applies to those who are interested in
actually practicing the Dhamma
not like practicing Dhamma because it
makes me feel good or helps movie things
but practicing the Dharma in the form of
in the way that the Buddha was teaching
the students which is basically undoing
your being undoing the power I'm doing
your sense of self so it's not it's not
something you can do on the weekends
only or on a 10-day retreat so your
whole life needs to start revolving
around it doesn't matter that life is in
a household setting or not and so you
have to you have to recognize that that
there is a there is a certain there's a
certain kind of what kind of natural
tendency Tennessee of in your own mind
to lean towards finding that excuse they
will remove that sense of guilt or
pressure that you might feel upon you
when you recognize that certain values
certain things that you value yourself
are being contradicted by your very life
style and your very actions so it seems
to be an automatic thing whereby people
who think that if I'm not a monk I don't
need to be sense restrained and and
that's just silly because the only the
only time that would be accurate thing
to say oh I'm not a monk I don't need to
be sensed Rainey's if you don't want to
practice Dhamma
then yeah you don't need to be sent
restraint is anything but the slight is
familiar to be the suitors will just
show what a silly view this is because
if you want to practice the Dharma the
original Dhamma without the basis of
Silla and sense restraint how good how
well established that basis is that's
how how how well the Dhamma will grow or
not and even even and that's the case by
the way food for the monks and laypeople
is no different today in that sense and
even those the the other hand softer the
Buddhist passing away when they met in
in the first council when they were
deciding what should I decide first the
suitors Dhamma suitors or Venus with the
origin stories of the rules and presets
they have unanimously decided to China
to decide the rules first the origin
story of how every rule came to be an
Emmy because they said the original demo
without sila
so yes sila is not the Dharma but there
is no Dharma without the sila so if you
think you can practice the Dharma
without a sense restraint the true
you're saying ah you found a way to
practice the Dharma without sila and
that's something even Buddha himself
could not have found because there isn't
one so then how much you will progress in
so then how much you will progress in
your life setting will depend how well
your sense restraint so you can have
duties and responsibilities and work and
all of that will be putting you know
stress on you and everything else but
none of that can be a reason for being
unrestrained so how well you develop
that restraint in that a diverse
environment of constant distraction
pressure demands of others from others
and so on
that's how well you will progress so
that's why you would people would go
forth and change the environment not
because somehow magically by putting on
robes sense restrain you just becomes
easy and you go and you're just flying
effortlessly no it's just simply because the
no it's just simply because the
environment is more suitable for sense
restraint because you wouldn't have to
deal with so many things distracting
all the time so I'm saying if there is a
reason that you cannot do that that's
still the principle of the practice does
not change it doesn't care for your
reasons basically so if you have a
reason for that prevents you from going
forth and entertaining that's fine but
that reason cannot become your
justification not for lack of sense
restraint for for lack of celibacy and
so on
so how far you want to progress in
practices how far you want to be
restrained I think I don't chance said
something like if you give up little you
will find little peace if you give up
more if I'm more peace if you give
everything up you'll find the ultimate
peace so nobody is excused from that
principle if you want to you know have a
mediocre progressing Dhamma so to speak
have some sense of greatest spiritual
purpose they will not require you to
give things up significantly and it will
not require you to experience the pain
of sense restraint sometimes four days
in that lay setting then then I guess 5
presets would be enough and but you
can't really regarded as a significant
progress in the Dhamma
I mean back in the day when the Buddha
like first off the heaven really for
most of their life they haven't even
thought the Dhamma to laypeople because
he will make him give up the lay life
and it was only when I'm at the pinnacle
on his deathbed so they put their giving
the teaching that made himself and I
said oh why didn't you want to teach
this to lay people before and and then
beg him to do so because there are those
people who will be able to understand
yeah so vast majority won't because
whilst majority will find it too
unpleasant to redraw themselves from
sensuality while they live in the
central world but there are those who
can't do it and so then even even those
people who who understood the diamond
practiced they done so because their
lifestyle was already being aligned with
it and they were making effort they have
not him people have not magically become
in the suitors as householders and then
started practicing sense restraint which
seems to be what people expect nowadays
now they've been sense restrained
they've been virtuous they've been
generous they've been obviously
contemplating Dhamma rightly as a result
of it they have become free from
sensuality completely develop Janice
completely and so on so it's important
to accept that responsibility
they will prevent you from using your
situation as an excuse and they will
basically outline exactly how much you
can progress because you will know how
much you can be sensed restrained and to
that extent you will create a basis for
the Dhamma to apply to like you can know
all the suitors and everything but if
there is no basis of virtue as those are
handset none of that will have any
fertile ground to grow from so
consequently if you have a well
thoroughly high-quality established
virtue and very little knowledge of the
Dhamma it will still grow because the
the fertile ground is there and it's
it's very potent so to speak so it comes
down to that to how willing you are to
take the pains of sense restraint and if
you if you want to make significant
strides the world's freedom from
suffering yeah you have 20 million for
for celibacy even as a household like
the ones in the sutras if back then
sense restraint was necessary you can
only imagine how much more so it is
today it's simply not optional and and
the the aim should be also for that for
that sense restraint is like a lifetime
goal not not something I'll do over the
weekend and hopefully understand the
Damned over the weekend and then I can
go back to my lay under strain ways it
needs to be taken on as a value and then
even if you sometimes might slip back
break the priests it's a loose sense
restraint the value remains there is
something they will pull you
back towards the top of the right
direction but if you if you don't value
it in that ultimate sense is something
to be ultimately developed and
maintained then you're not you will not
be restrained even when you are so to
speak it's like for example in which
people try to give up an addiction say
smoking it's much harder to give it up
if your decision to give up but thanks
for the rest of your life so if if you
say I will never smoke again for the
rest of my life you will feel the weight
of that much more then if you just try
and give up smoking and well let me see
how I feel I won't smoke for a while
then sometimes people can go for months
without cigarettes but they never really
stop smoking and they will always have
to go back to it always the only way to
not come back to it is to have aimed at
an ultimate value that you will never
smoke again then even if you fail and go
back to it that ultimate value will keep
you in the right direction and and in
that sense that guilt that was talking
about in the beginning of this video is
useful it will realign you with that
which you value which is why I feel
guilty so the worst thing is to to try
and justify it and cover it up and
psychologize your way out of it so you
don't feel discomfort there is a good
type of discomfort like guilt on account
of losing the virtue losing the sense
restraint is a good guilt
it's what the Buddha said that's what
protects the world from from doing your
immoral acts you will feel unpleasant
you will feel ashamed and you will have
a sense of like fear because what you
value you went against it and noticed
that if you practice like that you will
also be able to see these things
unwholesome things even before you
commit to them before you act out of
them the choice of either choosing
wholesomer and also would be much more
clearly outlined for you so how to
progress as a layperson in the Dhamma is
really comes down to deciding how far
you want to progress in that practice if
you are clear how far you want to go
then it will be clear to you how far you
should be restrained and how far you
need to make that effort of enduring the
discomfort of of a household environment
and it will also then make your efforts
towards a Dhamma contemplation and study
much more efficient like for example
what the example I gave people naturally
think that avoiding an overcoming sense
of guilt is good but as you see in
yourself just now it's not always the
case because sometimes you might be
rightfully so feeling guilty on account
of something you've done and you should
not cover that up and do that pain that
remorse because it is reshaping the
value then in regard to thing you've
done so next time you won't make the
same mistake so you force yourself to
learn from it and that's that's really
the the unpleasant thing people think
you can you can learn the dumb and
practice them on your own terms but you
can't the only way to do it rightly is
to set yourself up for being towards
that practice in other words set
yourself up to prevent yourself from
being from choosing the non practice
let's put it like that
so to practicing sense restraint to
acknowledging the guilt when you go for
wrongdoing of losing that sense
restraint to not using environment as an
excuse you set yourself up towards
facing basically that which needs to be
dealt with which is avoiding the pain
avoiding the suffering avoiding the
discomfort and that's always the root of
the entire sensual world the only reason
people go back to sense desires or
pursue the sense desires is because it's
too unpleasant to not do so and that for
people would then develop the view and
try to justify that no you don't need to
be sense restrained and you can practice
our minds all of that even say even if
they were theoretically true it's not
true individually because individually
it's always rooted in trying to avoid
pain so what you're saying is yes you
can free yourself from pain by trying to
avoid pain by pursuing distraction from
pain you will find a way out of pain and
that's complete calm
diction in terms if you are willing so
if I said if you if you if you sort of
block all these escape routes the
ignorant mind has of ignoring
psychologizing avoiding justifying then
you will you will start to face that
which pain will is and you don't need to
wait for misfortunes to happen to you or
or all sorts of types of you know
suffering things that are not to control
they will eventually you just need to
start practicing sense restraint and
you're gonna have a pure undulated pain
of your resistance and and that's what
practices finding the way out of it
without resorting to an external means
so if something gets too much well
that's why you start gradually Five
Precepts it please it occasionally but
again not I'll do this for a week and
then whatever hopefully I'll be coming
out and then I won't have to make the
effort ever again no needs to be the
value for the rest of your life so even
if you can only do it for a week you
still value it there's something to be
done again and again and again and that
that is a that is a lifetime work and
more than enough basis for sufficient
practice and yes you could then expect
the results such as overcoming
sensuality being completely almost
completely free from suffering as much
as a Anan egami would be and that is
possible in the house for life but that
is not possible with other sense
restraint in the house for life